[Music]
this is a film with aisha akanbi
who is a stylist and cultural
commentator probably best known for her
film
the problem with wokeness that went
viral a couple of years ago
i think wokeness has robbed many a
people of
compassion and replaced it with moral
superiority compassion and empathy
is paramount to any social movement and
to any form of progress
once you have compassion and empathy you
can often see that
you have a lot more in common with
people than you do apart and it's the
system under which we live in
that forcefully tries to group us on our
differences
what is radical is kindness what is
radical is understanding that's the one
thing they don't want us to do is to
understand each other arguing with each
other isn't actually radical at all it's
very conformist actually i do think that
wokeness does run the risk sometimes
in reducing very complex issues wokeness
tends to be quite reactionary instead of
responsive
and so when you react you go off of
motion and you go off of anger
resentment humiliation
and that doesn't necessarily leave much
space for nuance and nuance is important
in order to understand the
interconnectedness of the issues
and i think it's fair to say that the
issues that she talked about in that
film
have become even more relevant in the
time since
so i caught up with her in london to
talk about many things including how her
life has changed
since that film came out that was the
first thing i'd ever done that went
viral and
that was really scary actually um i
really didn't expect it to
at all and maybe something i didn't
fully appreciate at the time was
i think right now it's very rare to see
someone
with my identity essentially
who is willing to say those things in
public um
i didn't actually know at the time that
they were controversial
i just really thought this was common
sense and i think it is
to many people which is why it's so
maddening that we're in this position
that we're in right now
and the paradox of her talking about how
we needed to get beyond the politics of
identity
but her words being taken more seriously
and having more resonance
because of her identity i'm being honest
and i'm speaking from my heart
and i'm glad that it resonates with
people but the idea
that it should only resonate with people
because i am black is something that's
hard for me to
um to swallow and digest because
i don't know i just think we're we're
allowing ourselves to um
we're creating the ground to be easily
manipulated
if we're only going to take someone at
their word because of their identity
um because yeah it's not actually that
important to me if i'm honest like
being black being a woman my sexuality
these are probably the least interesting
things about me
um and i do
think that we'll be in a good place when
they're the most the least interesting
things about
us all and how her criticisms of
ideology
came from a really deep spiritual
transformation that she'd gone through
although what i'm doing can be seen as
political and i understand that
um it's very much not that as far as i'm
concerned
it's very much a a spiritual
kind of journey that i'm just sharing
out loud with people
and i see the spiritual journey as
trying to um trying to get towards
truth you know and allowing oneself to
be curious and i find a lot of these
movements to be
anti-curious and that's very troublesome
for me because
as long as we're not curious we won't
understand things and as long as we
don't understand things
those things can control us for me what
i find
so powerful about your that film and
your work more generally is that you're
coming from a very empathetic place
i think there are lots of people now
saying controversial things or pushing
back on wokeness
but it often feels like it's coming from
a quite a reactionary place
and there's a there's a huge market for
that as well but what i love about your
the way you framed is that you framed it
in a very empathetic way and
in a way it's like that the floor with
wokeness as an ideology is that it's
a performative empathy but it's not
actually particularly empathetic
how do you how do you frame that how do
you how do you kind of keep that empathy
when you're
talking about these things well i think
it's always important to remember
your own sort of humble you know
beginnings in terms of
your own thoughts and ideas and i was
very much someone at one point who was
quite susceptible
to some woke ideas what i think a large
section of the left i think they're very
um
fixated on being socially aware that's
what it is to be workers to be socially
aware
and what i really think it would really
benefit from
is if the mission statement was to
be as self-aware as it is socially aware
to prioritize um self-reflection
um but i don't often think it does that
because it positions itself as you know
being on the right side of history it's
one of the good guys and the problem is
when you consider yourself
solely through the lens of being a good
person is that
um you don't often feel the need to
self-reflect that's for everybody else
even in the word woke suggests to me
that they are looking for some
form of awakening you know but the
problem with the word woke is that it's
finished it's not awakening it's not
waking it's you know
done we know it all you know it's like
saying enlightened
what i think is missing from their
methodology
is maybe like a degree of um
a sort of like humanistic or spiritual
type of you know framework uh it doesn't
have that
i think it lacks a lot of humility
there's the paradox that you're
saying that you'd like identity
characteristics to be much less
important
but there is you are being listened to
partly because of your identity
characteristics and
you're able to say certain things that
if i was to say for example they would
they would not be taken as seriously
because people would assume that i'm
defending male privilege or um white
privilege or something like that
how do you kind of square that paradox
it's
it's somewhat bittersweet um because i'm
very aware that a lot of what i'm saying
can only be said by someone who looks
like me and i wonder how long i can even
say it
you know i mean i haven't uh there's
been no sort of campaign to cancel me
yet
uh but i won't hold my breath on that
because you know
it it comes for everyone eventually
um but what i
what i say to a lot of people when they
um they are
uh responsive to the things i'm saying
and they're taking something positive
from it
you know i let them know that i mean
there is no difference from me saying
this
and some you know a white man you know a
white straight man like
i could have all types of intentions
that you know you wouldn't be aware of
you can't just subject you can't just
think
because i am black you know that that is
a um i don't know that sort of purifies
you know this message i mean i'm being
honest and i'm speaking from my heart
and i'm glad that it resonates with
people but the idea
that it should only resonate with people
because i am black is something that's
hard for me to
um to swallow and digest because
i don't know i just think we're we're
allowing ourselves to
um we're creating the ground to be
easily manipulated
if we're only going to take someone at
their word because of their identity
um because yeah it's not actually that
important to me if i'm honest like being
black
uh being a woman my sexuality these are
probably the least interesting things
about me
um and i do think that we'll be in a
good place when they're the most
the least interesting things about us
all you know and that doesn't mean again
that i'm saying that we should
um deny where we're from and deny that
we have cultures that are different and
and we can learn and borrow and and and
mix
uh from that place um
but it's not you know it's not
fundamental um
i don't know that david i think it's a
it's a tricky one
knowing that i can only say this because
of
my identity but at the same time i mean
it needs to be said
you know it very much needs to be said
and
um it needs to be said by i guess
someone who
you know you can't easily read some sort
of ill intention from
um but yeah i don't know at the same
time i
i would encourage people uh in
to know that you know your identity is
not synonymous with virtue
you know like anyone can be unintended
or well intended
watching some of the the interviews with
you before doing this i was
really struck by how much you've gone on
a personal spiritual journey
do you think that influences your
understanding of the sort of ideologies
yes completely you know i often think
it's
a bad word because i'm not a bad word
but it's an unhelpful word because it
has so many connotations the word
spiritual
um but i perceive the word spiritual to
be
um an uncovering of yourself you know an
uncovering of yourself and through that
uncovering
uh the discovery or redefinition of
those people that are around you
and and that's the frame through which i
understand
most things if not all things um so
although what i'm doing can be seen as
political and i understand that
um it's very much not that as far as i'm
concerned
it's very much a um a spiritual kind of
journey that i'm just
sharing out loud with people um and i
see the spiritual journey as
trying to um trying to get towards truth
you know and allowing oneself to be
curious and i find a lot of these
movements to be
anti-curious and that's very troublesome
for me because
as long as we're not curious we won't
understand things and as long as we
don't understand things
those things can control us because i
i do believe a lot of those people are
on a search
um what they may be searching for they
may not know
but it's a search and
you know when i realized that the thing
that i was looking for
couldn't really be found externally you
know i tried to find a tribe i tried to
find a group
and i recognized there was too much of a
compromise
of principles sometimes values
things that are honest to you in order
to get this group membership
um you couldn't truly be yourself you
know and
and it felt to me that part of this
journey was about
truly getting to to know yourself um so
it just wasn't compatible but
you know i think when we have a more of
um
a holistic understanding of ourselves i
do think it really shifts the way that
we see other people
you know i think is there's that saying
you know we don't really see people
how they are we see them how we are um
so
it's within my interest and you know
what i encourage
for people to truly get to know
themselves in the most expansive way
possible
because then we um extend that to
everyone else
i remember before this journey happened
it felt like a dark night of the soul
because before this um
kick started i remember being in bed and
it was a
tearful night and i didn't expect it to
be i wasn't necessarily
sad but i remember all of a sudden my
mind just uh played a slideshow of all
these
unsettling um questions you know so
i was asking myself you know who was i
jealous of or what you know what made me
envious and
why i was doing the job that i wanted to
do and who are my friends and
you know like are you is this love or
are you bored just you know all these
kind of questions and
um all the answers to the questions at
that point were so uncomfortable and
they were so
raw that i just sort of melted if i'm
honest and
i just never been the same since and for
a long time it was
very um it was a very
sort of it was a journey that was full
of a lot of anguish and
and full of a lot of pain but it was all
very necessary to go through
yeah and i really am grateful you know
if there's anything i call a privilege
it's
that experience where how would you
describe where you find yourself now
at the end of that um i i don't know
that i'm at the end of that
you know to be honest but i'm in a much
more still place now
and i don't have a tribe you know
it doesn't feel like i i don't feel like
i want one i
i still don't identify politically it's
it's not a language i'm fluent in
um and i think you know i i just see my
my role here is to be as understanding
as possible
and to try and speak in a way that can
be
felt and understood by anyone
um regardless of your education level
you know i truly believe that we can say
anything but it's just about
learning how to say those things um
so yeah i'm i'm you know i'm just here
to connect with people you know whoever
is also um committed to some kind of
honesty or self-awareness
uh but i don't know where i am if i'm
honest yeah
i don't know where i am but it feels
like it's quite a solitary place still
yeah yeah i was struck i i'm struck by
just how much parallels there are
between
your journey and the journey of my
journey and rebel wisdom and just this
sense of
i feel like we all have to kind of cross
this this this valley in some way i
don't know how to define it but just in
the process of individuation and then we
spoke just before
recording and i mentioned i was familiar
with carl jung and you're like oh yeah
i'm really familiar with carl jung but i
don't normally talk about this
um what what maps or what kind of
thinkers do you find
most useful to understand or to navigate
the
the journey that you've been on
definitely uh
carl jung for sure um you know
what what jung says about
the shadow self you know and and
integration uh that's really important
in my world
and i think a lot of my work
is is trying to get people to embrace
the shadow
more is to acknowledge it and to know
that it's there first
because i don't know if everyone knows
that it's there and and to not judge it
you know because as long as we are
judging these uh undesirable aspects of
ourselves we're going to be defensive
about them and we're going to avoid them
but if we can learn to just see them
as is as opposed to this is bad
you know um that for me is very helpful
um and also it's it's once you know your
shadow or you can see it you're in
dialogue with it
it's much harder to be demeaning to
other people
you know for the same type of shadow um
so yeah i find carl jung to be uh very
um
enlightening and helpful uh people like
alan watts
um comedian like uh
george carlin i think he was brilliant
um eric fromm you know someone his book
i read
recently uh i i read the art of loving
yeah that was really something and you
know has helped
and also i'm quite into taoism um
i find the paradox to be um
really familiar you know it's really
familiar to the way that
my brain works i understand it you know
when i was in school i i wasn't
particularly a good student you know
like i had
all these learning difficulties you know
dyslexia i'm on the spectrum
and um adhd and
yeah so much of like the formal
education
was fairly lost on me uh and then i
remember when i came
across um dow teaching
i remember when i came across that and a
lot of might know it's quite a simple
book and it's very small
and loads of people like i just don't
understand this it makes no sense and i
was like this is the first thing that's
ever made sense
you know um so that was really
instrumental
in in me coming across um and i would
say it's very much like a bible to me
it's something i
often go back to um so yeah i mean
anyone who has like an element of
mysticism
within them somewhere even if they they
never use such words like
but some people have a certain type of
energy i don't know you know a lot of
people that you've even had on this
channel yeah i've this is a channel
actually you know genuinely i don't take
in very much
actually i'm not just saying this
because i'm on it but
um this is a channel that i have yeah
found deeply
helpful because you know you're
interested in the
the other side of you know the
conversation which doesn't get a lot of
attention
as he was saying something about jung
that struck me because i've had this
conversation recently about
that awareness of the shadow and the
the necessity of kind of sitting with it
when we react to something out there
and not immediately kind of going that's
wrong
but what is it bringing up in me and
you've talked about curiosity as this
really important value
but that seems essential i mean for woke
culture
in particular or at least sort of cancel
culture the sort of woke culture of
that's wrong we need to change it to be
able to realize well no actually that's
bringing up something in me that i need
to look at
seems like an essential piece and i
don't want to just limit it to that
because we see that on the right just as
much as the left and we see cancel
culture on
on all sides of the political spectrum
like there are certain taboo topics
wherever you come from
i would probably agree that it seems
more prevalent on the left because it's
kind of the
the head cultural hegemony at the moment
is more on the left and the right but
that awareness and that self-awareness
seems so crucial and i think that's what
i
also really recognize in the the
perspective that you're bringing because
you you really understand that i feel
yes are i often think that
whatever is most aggravating to us and
anything that
elicits this sort of visceral response
or reaction that you can't control
i think is an unchecked part of yourself
you know
and so i know the moments when there's
someone that i just
for no reason i sort of instinctively
dislike which is rare
but when that does happen i'm like oh
your body's telling you something
oh here's something you haven't dealt
with um and so i'm much more even when
it comes to
uh wokeness you know it's a question i
have to ask myself
what is this bringing up you know why is
it that you don't like this or
what's so incompatible and of course
there are all of the um
legit concerns about you know i i see it
as an anti-curious movement
i see it as selling self-sabotage under
the banner of empowerment
you know i i see it doing i see it as
aggravating
racial tension um all of that is true
however there might be this other
element that is
well you used to be like this a little
you know you used to be like this and
and have you have you forgiven yourself
for that
you know and so what i see in
a lot of the council culture it seems to
me and a lot of the
this need and desperation to point out
who's wrong
you know and and make people accountable
this is something i hear people say a
lot these days you know
he needs to be accountable um and i find
it very interesting
just even that thinking that it's your
job to make other people accountable
it seems to me that people are
witnessing in other people who they used
to be
you know and they're overcompensating
for that so when they see someone doing
something they don't like it's
less about what that person is doing and
more about advertising well look at who
i am look at who i am no longer
you know it's more about i guess or even
sometimes disowned parts of themselves
yes
exactly that um so yeah i see that's
what it is i you know i i think i wrote
it down the other day somewhere
it feels like a war with the
unconsciousness
yeah and i think that's something that
really i don't think there's any way out
of this
culture war dynamic that just seems to
be accelerating
without that that acceptance or that
kind of
dropping into a much deeper perspective
that involves psychology that involves
uh mythology that involves the
mythopoetic dimension
and certainly the psychological
dimension but i would argue like the
the personal growth or the spiritual
dimension as well i don't think there's
a way out from the
from just the sort of the surface level
yeah no i don't think so i mean
a lot of what people of course you know
there needs to be um
um aspects of political reform and
governmental change and
um you know systemic things happening
um however i often do see a lot of what
people
are looking for externally is is first
going to come by
um some personal transformation you know
maybe what some would call a spiritual
revolution
um some sort of shared understanding
about you know what we're doing here
you know and even if we have different
belief systems that's fine
but just um some type of shared
you know perspective of what it means to
be alive and to be human
it's going to pick up in the last in
your last comment you mentioned that you
felt that wokeness
um aggravates racial tensions i kind of
have a feeling what you mean by that but
do you want to
kind of unpack that so when i say that
wokeness
aggravates racial tension what i mean is
you know it acknowledges rightfully that
racism still exists you know i think it
will
be something that always exists because
you know we humans
are complicated people but the way that
it tries to
um counter you know and reduce maybe
some
of those racist attitudes that exist i
think
often can exacerbate them and so
when we are speaking about entire
demographics whether they be white men
white women um in ways that we
would shudder you know break down and
just sort of completely erupt out if
anyone
did the same if someone painted you know
you know black groups as this one
monolithic
negative thing um it would just be
chaos you know and so whether it's well
intended
whether it's even maybe historically
true or something like that whatever it
may be whatever the justification is
it just it doesn't play into
our human natures very well you know you
can't
you can't make blanket statements about
all one people
and think that you know this is not
going to give other people license to
think well okay well if
you know we're all white and fragile
well then maybe you're all
black and frail or whatever it may be
you know like
it's just um it just seems to be
the most corrosive way to try and
understand one another um and even the
idea that we need to
be hyper aware now of other people's you
know
race and stuff like that whereas you
know it seemed like
you know before that it wasn't so much
of
of an issue you know i could my my
friends who are not black could speak to
me about anything
and i wouldn't feel the sort of the
treading on eggshells whereas now i can
see the treading on eggshells i can see
people not trying to
offend me and maybe some might say that
you know people are just becoming more
thoughtful but
i don't know if we're becoming more
thoughtful i think we're becoming more
fearful
yeah it's it's something about making
these categories primary
seems incredibly dangerous because it
brings you into kind of zero-sum game
like just acknowledging that that's the
primary way that we need to meet each
other i think is
that feels incredibly regressive to me
but also there's an angle there which
coleman hughes was talking to john
mcwater recently and he said
what he found powerful about martin
luther king was that martin luther king
had this
kind of spiritual like he was a
christian pastor and he was able to sort
of say
we're all one in the eyes of god and he
had this possibility of holding up this
sort of
other value system that wasn't just
uh identity politics and coleman asked
the question and i know you're talking
to him fairly soon so maybe i think this
would be a really interesting thing to
talk to him about
is it possible and he he questioned
actually whether it was possible
to have a kind of or whether you needed
that kind of religious
or spiritual perspective to be able to
kind of and i think you do
i think you do need some kind of
religious or transcendental
value to be able to unify beyond
because it's like we do need to be aware
of like there are racial disparities in
some areas there are different
experiences of the world that's
kind of for me just basic empathy it's
not it doesn't need to be formalized as
kind of intersectionality or this kind
of elaborate value system
but we have to have this sort of sense
of what are we beyond
what are we beyond that our identity
characteristics
i think that feels like a really
important distinction like we need to be
aware of it we can't hold it as primary
yes you know you're completely right and
i think what the thing is is because a
lot of people
don't have this um transcendental
framework
for many people i think their identity
is the extent of who they are
so you know i meet lots of people now
who are more likely to say well
you know i'm a feminist before human you
know or i'm a black
person before anything else um
and while i'm not saying that
anyone should have to negate you know
aspects of their identity but
we should be aware because we deserve to
know
in our very one short life and the only
provable life that we know
um that we are so much more than this
you know and i often think the fixation
with your identity you know limits your
identity in many ways
um because whilst you're thinking let's
say well i'm a man and i'm from here so
that means i can't do this i can't
listen to this i can't wear or
go here you know it's it's similar you
know we often think that well
i'm black and you know maybe you're
white so you can't understand my
experience
you can't know anything about what i've
been through we can't find a point of
relation
that's just not true um and i think we
know it's not true
um because whether it's discrimination
you may have experienced because of your
skin color maybe not but you could have
faced discriminations of other kinds
you know that can feel um just as
as powerful you know or just as hurtful
um
and we can relate there and even if you
haven't i just don't think
i would like to assume uh that the the
pigmentation of your skin means that you
lack empathy and you lack compassion
because the other side of that is then
maybe
uh you know me having this identity
means that i
could lack this and like they were
saying it's true for one then
you know there has to be something
undesirable that's true
on my side as well um so
yeah it just for the most part
fundamentally uh
why i think a lot of racial discussions
that we're having in public now
feel again quite corrosive is that it
just
feels dishonest to
our everyday interactions yeah and
there's something just very profoundly
unhuman about the idea that it's
impossible for me to
understand someone's experience like it
may be very difficult for me to
understand someone's experience but
by engaging in conversation by engaging
in
empathy by engaging in our human
capacities we can
empathize maybe i won't know fully what
it was like to live your life but i
but the idea that i cannot know possibly
there was a slogan during the recent
black lives matter uh protest which was
something like
i i understand i will never understand
nevertheless i stand as a kind of ally
and on the face of it
it was like yeah solidarity but but
within that felt like
i i was kind of very ambivalent about it
because it's like
i understand i will never understand
it's like that for me
is the death of empathy it's the death
of
art it's the death of so much of the
common human experience i think it just
it ends up siloing us off in a place
where we can never
get past like how how can we get if we
can't get past that
we can't have a like we're dooming
ourselves to kind of
isolation from each other yeah no
exactly and there's this assumption that
you know every black person can
understand you know the experience of
another which is also not true
you know like that's and we know it's
not true and so i don't know sometimes
if
we're saying things because you know uh
you know they're pithy and they sound
nice
and and so because they sound nice they
they should make sense
um but that's just yeah again
i think that's always what i just come
back to it's just it's just
not true there are plenty of black
people whose experience
i haven't had you know because it sort
of
works from this uh presumption that all
black people are experiencing the same
thing
you know and that we all feel that our
lives have been
minimized and reduced because of the way
other people perceive us
and that's not true no matter what
type of person you are you're always
going to have people project things onto
you
you know you're always going to have
maybe people uh
perceive you as something you may not be
i don't know if we can get away from
this in the human experience
um but to say that all of those
projections that other people have had
especially the negative ones
have to color my entire experience and
the entire way that i see myself
it's profoundly damaging to me i think
and it's just not true yeah i want to
talk a little bit about because i feel
like so much of this
conversation is being influenced by the
american conversation we seem to have
imported a lot of the categories
wholesale
and i think there are very different
dynamics there that are that are very
that are completely different like the
legacy of slavery and the legacy of
kind of redlining and long-term
disadvantage
are very different and i i guess you're
nigerian originally so you don't have
the same background in slavery i'd be
really interested in sort of those
differences
i often don't feel like i see
enough of a meaningful difference in the
conversations
again i think you said it you know it
does seem like we import
the conversation wholesale and you know
apply it to the uk and i'm not sure if
that's
wise i mean it's not even that i'm not
sure i don't think that's wise to do
because they are different there are
different legacies and
and different present day um issues
um and i guess this is the uh the issue
with the internet i guess is that it
doesn't
leave much space for for difference and
nuance and complication
um but no i don't personally think i
see much of a difference you said you
have no one's tried to cancel you yet
what are the criticisms that you've had
um
you know what i'm again i've been fairly
lucky
and maybe the next time i come back and
speak to you or be a completely
different story
um but i don't actually get much
pushback and i don't actually get much
criticism
um at least i've seen and i don't go
looking through comments
every now and then i get someone message
me um and may say that your world view
seems very privileged
it seems that something like only a
privileged person could do
because you know i often say that you
know we're more than our identities
and some people think that well i can't
be more than my identity because
wherever i go
my identity is made an issue it's a
problem
um and i will dialogue with this person
back and i'll just say
well again you you can't
you can't base your identity and sense
of self on the people who misunderstand
it
you know that doesn't seem like a
healthy way to live
you know of course people read me in all
kinds of ways
whether that is about my race sexuality
or you know
just gender whatever the way i present
myself i'm sure
lots of people have stereotypes
sometimes
that's also not my problem you know it
doesn't have to be you know your problem
so i think there is some people um
who might think i have a romantic
privileged um kumbaya
way of seeing the world um
and i i don't i don't think so of course
um
uh i do think it's a privilege to
finally recognize that we have
more in common than we do apart uh i
don't think we have to be privileged
to come across this type of information
but it is a very big privilege
onto the self when we do um
see this and it makes our navigation
through life a lot more enriching
and you can really have some truly
beautiful connections when you do open
yourself up to this
uh way of seeing and what are the
conversations that you feel are not
happening at the moment because for me
certainly i feel
there's an amazing podcast recently with
uh brett weinstein
had a black intellectual round table
with um
colin hughes chloe valderry john wood jr
john mc water glenn lowry and thomas
chatterson
thomas chaston
um which was amazing like it was it was
they certainly had very different views
some were
kind of pro reparations some were not
but they were all
grappling with this sort of conversation
about
how much of the underachievement of the
black community in america for example
is to do with
structural racism how much is it to do
with ongoing discrimination
how much is it to do with historical
factors how much to do with cultural
factors
and it feels like for me the big problem
is that we're in a
we're in a world view that seems to only
the only acceptable explanation seems to
be ongoing
discrimination right now and that seems
like a very narrow
perspective because i feel like we have
to bring in all of these different
frames to be able to understand it
what are the what are the things that
you feel are not being the conversations
are not being had
yeah i would say as far as racial
discourse goes
i i think we need to be able to give
equal weight to all of those things so
whether they are
cultural factors we can look at systemic
issues i mean that
is predominantly what we do right now
you know we don't really give much space
to anything else something that i'm very
interested in is
um is the self-esteem of uh
minority people so whether that is
whether this is someone who feels
marginalized by their sexuality someone
who feels marginalized by their race
um self-esteem i think um plays a
big factor in how you see the world and
how you see yourself
irrespective of what barriers may exist
may or may not exist
um and so that is something that i think
is crucial and is something that i
i hope to encourage to raise
throughout my work because then
it's much easier to to live in a world
where you know because
we can't control other people people
will always um
be fearful if they want to be fearful
discriminatory if they want to be
discriminatory
and so on and so forth but you can
change how you see yourself
you can change how you deal with such
situations
um and when we recognize for me when it
comes to a lot of let's say actual
racist people which i i meet less and
less
uh which is good but like you know i
recognize
racism to be a um
sort of like a reflection of one's own
ignorance um lack of understanding of
their own selves like inferiority
you know and so it's it's not
threatening to me
you know it's something i pity you know
it's not something that
um it's not something that can
i don't know necessarily outrage me in
such a way
and i think we need to spend more time
um
philosophically maybe trying to
understand and emotionally what is
racism you know underneath it all like
actual racism
uh not just the way that we throw around
the time you know
the way that we throw around the time
white supremacist or something like that
you know i think we need to actually
think about how do people
you know harbour these views and and not
just white people because again you know
i think everybody can be racist or be
racially discriminatory
um it's just semantics uh if you don't
want to use the term racism because you
don't think black people can be racist
racist whatever but we can still be
racially discriminatory and
prejudice um and i think
we need to be able to um
we need to be able to contend with
people who might have bigoted views
without necessarily saying that that
means their whole
entire character is utterly flawed and
you know we should put them in the bin
because it's going to be harder for
people to
acknowledge that they have some biases
and maybe some negative racial
stereotypes
if we are also saying well this means
that you are a hideous you know morally
and pure person it's irredeemable
no one is going to want to self-reflect
under such an environment
um so for one i think we should stop
necessarily treating
racist attitudes as like the ultimate
moral sin
if i'm honest um because it's ignorant
and it's foolish but it's definitely
not something that makes you an
irredeemable person who should be cast
out of public life
i i think we need to communicate with
each other more
um sorry this was a really long way of
doing this your question actually was
though
um what are we not talking about
um so in terms of yeah
we're not talking about i would i would
agree with a lot of the conversations
that happened on brett weinstein's uh
podcast i do think we need to
pay attention to the things outside of
discrimination because
in one's own life it's rare that the
things
that are making your life difficult are
solely about this external factor
it's very very very rare you know even
if we think about a romantic
relationship
this romantic relationship breaks down
it's
very rare that it's solely the other
person you know who's making this
relationship break down
you know even if they have the more
hostile aggressive behavior
the question will soon return why am i
still in this you know
and so i do think we um
yeah we need to be able to look at
reasons beyond discrimination
without without um without being
defensive you know without
suggesting that people who want to have
that conversation are ill-intended
anybody who really cares about
marginalized people black people and
really wants to see
um the black race you know get to a
get to a point that is a bit more
progressive or whatever
um you are going to want to think about
it from all angles you have to
you know otherwise you are kind of like
shooting your own aims in the foot
so yeah i think we have to that is what
it means to care
is to look at all aspects and
what i've really loved just listening to
some of your podcasts and then we've
exchanged a few messages
is in rebel wisdom we've got kind of a
few different frameworks that we talk
about and we've talked about kind of
polyvagal theory and the value of
curiosity we've talked about
integral theory and the value of kind of
multiple perspectives
and you are you're talking about all of
all of the same stuff you're basically
he sent me a message saying
how valuable curiosity was and i was
like oh you've heard of polyvagal theory
and you're like no it's like you've
heard of integral theory no
it's like so so refreshing um
that because i speak to a lot of people
who are kind of saying a lot of the same
uh things but i've often got a kind of
theoretical background in this
in this world or they're using a map
that they've got from sort of
somewhere or other but you're you've
kind of very
directly kind of made your way there
under your own steam
which in some ways kind of reassures me
that those maps are actually pointing to
something real because you don't need to
know about them to be able to see that
um but i'm interested in asking you
about that especially curiosity
because you said something beautiful in
one of the messages that it takes you
somewhere
the value of it is that it takes you
somewhere new or that it's it's a very
sort of
it by definition it's a it's an
individual journey i think or something
can you talk a bit about curiosity yeah
um curiosity is probably
um something i value um
higher than most things i think when
we're curious about each other for one
i i think it allows us to see this
commonality that we have
um it makes us less
reactive and i think when you're i mean
you're curious
you know i don't think you have the same
rush to uh
to condemn i don't think you have the
same rush to criticize
um it's the foundation of understanding
and and i really just think that
understanding is
it's just so crucial you know i i i
don't think there's many sort of um
material things that i i value highly
but you know i'm very hyper aware that
this is a
very impermanent existence uh too hyper
aware
and so it seems to me that the best way
to honor that
uh that fact is to is to
be curious and is to um really get to
know ourselves while we're here
um so yeah i don't know i mean it just
it seems to be the foundation
of everything uh of everything
transformative
and that's why i think curiosity is
something we can't afford to lose
and especially right now when we're
living in this um attention
economy it's harder to be curious you
have to fight for your curiosity now
because you know we're told what to
believe and we're told
what we should be thinking about there's
also something about vulnerability that
that i think is really important like
that you you're prepared to talk about
kind of your doubts and your
your personal background as well in
public which i think is really important
as well and there seems to be something
about that that's necessary
again to get out of this situation that
we're in like just showing that we're
all human just showing that we all have
these yes of course like you know i'm
far from a yogi
you know and i i very much have my own
battles and struggles and issues with
self-doubt
um but you know i often think a lot of
the um
the mental sort of textures that we have
that are not very delightful
you know i really think they're there to
teach us something you know so even if
it's something like
anxiety i think anxiety is often a clue
you know
as to to that maybe you're you're
anxious around a certain someone or in a
certain space it's it's
tapping at you and saying like okay what
is it about this place or this person
that you know is not okay with me you
know it's asking you to do some work
and so yeah equally maybe even things
like depression like i think
if we're looking we can find um
use for these things doesn't mean i
think we have to we don't have to live
in these situations
but we can find use for them um and so
yeah it doesn't it doesn't make sense
for me to
to try and present someone that's i
don't know not human i
wouldn't be able to do that very well um
and there's something you said in your
um your talk about conflict is
conformist
which i think is really that's a really
important
thought especially now because we're
being pushed towards polarization and
division by
the big tech platforms because that
generates more interest the more
wired we are the more likely we are to
keep kind of checking twitter
seeing if anyone's replied to our kind
of comment on facebook like
they are we are being pushed more and
more towards
what we have tristan harris on our
podcast recently talked about the battle
to the bottom of the brain stem
like we're triggering for outrage we're
triggering for the more kind of primal
emotions
so i love that idea like conflict is
actually conformist it's really
beautiful
yeah i thought about doing putting on a
t-shirt i know but i should do thank you
for that
um but it is i do believe conflict is
conformist because it's knee-jerk
you know it's it's it's just so
reactionary and it's just what we've
always done
you know we've always had conflict with
each other but it's very rare that we've
been able to understand each other it's
very rare that we can sit with something
deeply uncomfortable or deeply
disagreeable to our ideas
and rather than condemn someone for them
but ask
why do you have these ideas you know
it's that
takes uh that to me is a radical act
because
it's harder to do we're not encouraged
to do it there's less applause for doing
it
you know someone might say you're
humanizing the oppressor or something
like that or an abuser
um but if it's happening within humans
then it is human we know we need to
humanize it we need to
you know humanizing it doesn't
necessarily mean condoning such behavior
it just means that
you are prepared to explore it um
so uh sorry what was the thing that you
said
conflict so um how did i get back into
that
and so these are the reasons as to why i
think conflict is conformist because
it's unthinking you just do it but to
to be more understanding is a considered
you know response
you know it's it's practice it's it's
trying to overcome your compulsions how
do we do it
how do we do it david it's a good
question
we do it i think one of the principal
ways that we do it
is um by
recognizing and fully contending with
our own
capacity for destruction you know
really holding the the ugly
parts of what it means to be human and
recognizing that they are in
us um and then maybe thinking about
what prevents us from maybe acting
within those ways you know maybe we've
had a great family
maybe we've had shelter support you know
education um and then recognizing where
those things may be missing for other
people
and i don't know you just start to
you just start to see people more
clearly yeah and and so i think
that is how we become more
more responsive and that's maybe how we
increase empathy
is by uh recognizing that maybe there
are no good people
there are only you know
people who are flawed trying to be
better that's it we're all at different
stages of that
yeah and i mean i have done a lot of
as i've talked about on the channel i've
done kind of a lot of kind of spiritual
work personal growth work
group work and there's something about
the energy that comes in when you're
really honest with someone like
you're kind of talking about your life
you're sharing kind of personal stuff
and you just
realize that there's a there's a space
that comes in there's a feeling of
actual togetherness that kind of you
could criticize as being like a
it's a very middle-class affectation
it's something that kind of
yeah it's something that some people can
do but a lot of people can't afford to
and i an experience not that long ago
where i volunteered for a group called
band of brothers
so they do mentoring for disadvantaged
kids basically people who just come out
the criminal justice system
and they match people up with mentors
they go through a kind of rite of
passage
and i volunteered with them in in
hackney and it was
by far the most racially mixed group
i've kind of
not just racially mixed but also mixed
in terms of class there was a
there's a lot of kind of working-class
jamaican guys working-class kind of
different africa caribbean communities
and
what was astonishing is that everyone
had the background of sort of
having gone through this rite of passage
talking about themselves talking about
their struggles
their hopes their fears their weaknesses
and it it was kind of it was magical
what happened like that was genuine
community
and i feel like a lot of the time
especially kind of guilty white liberal
kind of want to be like oh no we're all
we're all together i'm i'm not racist
i'm
it's like there's a kind of efforting in
that sort of sense of multiculturalism
where you're not really sharing these
people's lives
you're going to come in and out of their
communities you actually struggle to get
your events looking anything like other
than just your
kind of white community there is
something about
if we're able to go into that space of
vulnerability
with each other that everyone no matter
where you're from no matter
what your class background is you have
struggles in your life you have
difficulties you have
beliefs about yourself that you can talk
about something
magical happens when we're able to go
into a space we're actually able to
express that
and that that for me seems to be just
such an important part of the
of the puzzle for like genuine humanity
genuine connection
and i feel like the problem is we're in
an environment especially with social
media that militates against any of that
like we don't share anything personal we
don't feel we're in a safe space to do
that because we're not a lot of the time
it might be taken against us it might be
taken out of context all of these sort
of things but it's
like that for me is the humanity somehow
needs to come back in i don't know i
don't know how we do it
but it just feels like that's a really
important yeah no i agree with you
i i think um honesty is that
thing that you know allows us to
transcend
all these shallow superficial
differences
um and we're so yeah you're right we're
not encouraged to be honest
we're encouraged to be right you know a
lot of the time and
we're encouraged to you know have a take
make a point you know maybe safe spaces
at their most effective would be good
if they actually brought people who are
unlikely to talk together
you know so uh interracial
intergenerational you know
left and right you know and and and hash
out things
i think that's probably i mean because
if you're if you're insulating yourself
around other people who are just like
you i mean that can happen
quite easily in life anyway without a
safe space you know it could just be
the area that you've grown up in in your
friendship groups
um but yeah i think safe spaces
um if there are to be any use for them i
think it's in bringing
different types of people together um
because we do
you know one of the issues i i think for
me
uh with this self-censorship that we're
all going through right now
is that there's a there's a there's a
mental consequence to this there's a
mental consequence and an emotional
consequence
to having to swallow everything to
being paranoid you know and thinking
that your friends are going to dislike
you
you know i don't know maybe they find
out that you listen to jordan pearson
you know or whatever it may be
you know thinking that um you know all
of these
paranoid thoughts that we have now you
know we kind of almost
maybe sensibly have to have um
i think there is a real consequence to
that that is not going to be
um useful or conducive
to the to the individual and to the
group
because we're sort of inviting everybody
to lie to us for
the sake of our own comfort you know and
i would rather
know about the world that i live in you
know as as
as ugly as it can be um and i think when
we're
equipped to to withstand
you know the uh the more undesirable
parts of humanity we might be equipped
to overcome some of it
did you listen to jordan peterson oh i
definitely did
no i think i mean i of course you know
there's probably things i i'd like to
discuss with him that i'm not
necessarily sure about but
you know i don't think jordan peterson
is
the the person that everybody thinks he
is you know i don't think he's
uh this evil conservative who's a bigger
and all those kinds of things i think he
represents uh as we can see
you know from his audience i think he he
represents a
feeling and a sense that a lot of people
feel um
and also with his more kind of spiritual
dimensions you know i think that's a
testament to how much
people want something like that people
are are desperate for something
uh that sounds or can feel hopeful
you know we keep hearing about what's
wrong with the world and
uh why it's terrible and why it doesn't
care about any of us i think you know
it's been a long time since someone's
come in and maybe said actually
you can make your life you know what you
want it to be
i think that's very very persuasive and
very encouraging for people
um yeah i'm cool with it yeah
and in the the conversation you had with
alan de botton
you talked about feeling lonely and
feeling that you needed community or
looking for community do you still feel
that way or do you feel that you're
finding more of it
i think i'm finding more of it i think
i've accepted that i'm quite
a solitary person um i think i'm
better without a group and without a
tribe
i think it allows me to make sure i'm
being honest with myself because i think
once i start feeling like
i want a political side or a home
somewhere
beyond myself that's when i might start
you know not saying certain things
because i don't know how these people
are going to take it
[Music]
so no i still don't i don't know if the
word is community
but i have a lot of loving um supportive
people in my life and
on the internet and and people who are
always saying the kindest things
considering we know we often think that
the internet and social media in
particular
is like a hell hole my experience there
is genuinely quite good
yeah people are really kind to me and
and often very encouraging
and i meet people of all types of all
across the political spectrum
like you know i have genuine maga
followers
and you know i've got some hardcore
marxists and
um it's nice to be able to
dialogue you know with both and sort of
just come in peace
it's nice and are you concerned about
how you could be potentially used or how
your words could be used
because it does there is such a thing at
the moment of kind of um guilt by
association of appearing on certain
podcasts that you may be seeing as a
certain a certain way
or do you do are you concerned about
that do you worry about
i mean like because i i personally i
think that what you
what you really offer as i've said is
this sort of this real level of empathy
but there is a market for kind of
anti-woke stuff and there is a sort of
temptation to be sort of maybe dragged a
little bit further and further into a
more reactive
space and i've seen that happen to
people over the last
few years there are some there are some
shows that become more and more
just let's bash the left let's bash the
left left is going crazy
and for me that's just adding to the
division rather than trying to hold up a
place
beyond it which is what i feel that
you're doing um
so i feel a little almost like a sense
of um
is it protection protection almost a
sense of protection is like you
yeah i would hate for that to happen i
don't think would happen to you
personally
but i am a little bit worried that you
might be sort of seen in a certain way
if you
if you are sort of seen as being aligned
with certain people
yes um i wish it wasn't something that i
had to consider but i do
consider it maybe not maybe not as
heavily as some people would like
because i feel if i'm too
hyper aware of who could use me
or who might misinterpret my message
then
i'm not gonna say what i think and that
for me is is worse that
that feels like a self-imposed prison um
so i don't want to do that but i think
i'm very aware of
you know i'm under no illusion about
why even you know i am in this in the
room
of certain conversations you know i'm
aware that it's my identity i'm aware
that i am saying things that a lot of
people
who don't look like me can't get away
with saying
um and so because i'm very hyper aware
of that
i it's quite easy to see and i don't i
don't blame them
you know i don't blame them i don't i
don't see it as
them even necessarily being ill-intended
you know like
we're all sort of possessed at the
moment with this
cultural stuff and this uh need to
prove that we are right
um i think i can feel it i think i can
spot it quite easily
um and yeah and so
that sort of that tells me and directs
me where i should go and where i
shouldn't go
um but the problem is or at least i i'd
like there to be
enough scope on you know maybe some
mainstream left channels
um for discussion because
that's the consequence you know if you
if you're not very
accepting of different viewpoints then
the only people who are going to pick up
you know nuanced viewpoints or anything
like that are going to be
people in the center or people on the
right people that you might
you know have some preconceived notion
of
so this is doubly why you know we need
to be able to open up conversation
on all sides so you're not slowly
pushing people
um to one place but no in an ideal world
i speak to everybody because you know i
i am genuinely interested in in everyone
and especially people who
do not see the world in the way that i
do um
but yeah no i'm i i think i've i've
i've got a good sense of you know where
to be and why
yeah because i i wish it didn't
it wasn't the case that you did have to
kind of be aware of that but i think you
do
but at the same time i think that you
have a possibility of being quite
a person who bridges different tribes
and this is something that we've talked
quite a lot about on the channel the
idea of memetic tribes
and memetic mediation which is like who
can talk
to these different tribes without
activating the immune system of the
different tribes you know certain topics
will activate the immune system
okay you're on that side or that side
and i think i'd love
to see i think you have the opportunity
to do that because i think you're
you're certainly coming from a very
empathetic place and i think that will
that will serve you well
in the future so i'm really looking
forward to seeing what you do next yeah
hopefully you know i'm i'm
i'm down to genuinely talk to anybody
who's willing to have respectful
conversation and who wants to
move past you know the conversations
into some kind of like action
um of how we can you know yeah try to
try to decrease the polarization and the
conflict
and yeah become more self-aware thank
you
thank you very much thank you rebel
wisdom was set up to make sense of the
world
at a deeper level than the mainstream
media it was built for these times of
crisis and change
which is why we want to do what we can
to meet the challenge of the times
more films and also for our rebel wisdom
members
weekly sense making calls with our
amazing interviewees
and also we're introducing the wisdom
gym
a place to practice some of the skills
that we've talked about on the channel
thanks for watching and see you soon